foreign
[Music]
good day everybody welcome back to the
ask budget show after a gap of a week I
hope you're all doing very well as you
know I've been busy traveling would you
like to see some travel pictures
here are some travel pictures check it
out
as you can see I'm getting progressively
more tired
and there you are
so yeah it's it's been all uh it's been
all airplanes and hotels good fun then
there's more of it to come the next week
or so
so yeah I've been busy traveling and I'm
very very happy to be back on the show
today right
so uh today is a live chat live chat uh
session and uh first of all let's see
who all is there with us let me see who
who all is what is here you can see uh
Rishi
the only 98 years ganga Singh Sky D
gaming Rahul Vanoss Hindus
knowledge with anadi partha day crazy
brain cha-ching priyanshu Karan Singh
route
and uh one tabs easy
Prius
Mahatma gandhiji is here with us
critical gray and lots of other people
good evening good day thank you for
being back on the show with me and yeah
so uh we're gonna take questions from
the live chat tomorrow I'm going to be
taking questions from the comments so if
you have questions for me let's get into
it start asking your questions and we
will discuss everything and anything
under the sun whatever you see fit let's
go ahead and do that
okay let's see
um Abhishek says have you ever read the
work of rajnish Osho
uh unfortunately I have not read any of
his works I am sure that he has a uh
written some books I'm sure and there
are lots of transcripts of his of his
speeches and his uh
uh what do they call them pravachans or
whatever it is yeah many of those things
are available online
so uh I'm sure one can buy that I
personally have never read any of that I
have seen some of his videos some of the
video clips he clearly was a very
intelligent person a very sharp person
and it could be quite humorous as well
he had a very wicked sense of humor
um very interesting person I remember
when I was a kid like you know when I
was like less than 10 years old
uh I was living in Europe at the time
and at that time I believe rajneesh Osho
was uh he had his uh commune or whatever
they call it in the United States
and yeah there was quite a buzz around
that
and eventually I think uh he came back
to India and they were all I mean that's
a whole very interesting very convoluted
story about uh rajneesh and his ashram
and his followers and uh there was there
were power struggles within his
followers you know within the the
society had created the community he had
created and so on very interesting story
I think he was a brilliant person uh
yeah so I have not read his works but I
think I may want to in the future if I
get the time right
all right let's go to swapnil why are
earthquakes so difficult to predict as
compared to other types of natural
disasters hashtag geophysics
right earthquakes you know the Indian
subcontinent
is an earthquake-prone region it's not
part of the belt of fire the belt of
fire is something that runs through
Indonesia Japan is part of it and you
know it's the entire rim of fire where
you have all the volcanoes and it's an
earthquake prone region the andamans is
part of that we have a couple of at
least one volcano two volcanoes I
believe in the Andaman uh archipelago
region you know volcanoes on Indian
Territory one is the narrow condom one
is the baron island volcano right
so India actually is an earthquake prone
region if you look at a larger time
period you see it a decade upon decade
you will not see much happening except
for smallish earthquakes but if you look
at it Century upon Century that way
they're going to have massive
earthquakes especially in the Himalayan
region which is still Rising it's very
tectonically unstable the Himalayas are
still rising in height every year it's
like a few
centimeters in a couple of centimeters
or so which seems to be very very small
from our perspective but overall it's
big you know so they're gonna rise much
higher in the future and we have
earthquakes in the Himalayan region
there was an earthquake I don't know two
three decades ago in the uh uttarakashi
region and more recently there was a
massive earthquake in Nepal
so it would certainly make a great sense
to develop means of predicting
earthquakes because earthquakes can be
very damaging they obviously destroy
property they destroy infrastructure but
also human life right so I'm sure you
cannot move infrastructure away it's all
built upon the land you can't move
infrastructure but you can certainly
save human lives if you are able to
predict the earth earthquakes even if
you have a lead time of 30 minutes you
can save a lot of lives if you know that
the the earthquake is going to happen so
why is it so difficult to predict
earthquakes well the reason for that is
because earthquakes uh originate in a
Subterranean tectonic activity so below
the surface of the Earth we have various
layers of the Earth right let's let's
look it up what are the layers
layers of Earth let me put that on the
screen
where are we here we are
layers of Earth that's the Google search
I'm doing and hopefully it'll show us
something interesting
so
okay these are the various layers you
have the Earth's crust you have the
mantle the outer core the inner core so
and uh below the crust you have the
mantle which essentially is is magma
magma is what comes out to the surface
as lava all right that's what we see uh
that erupts from volcanoes
and then there is I don't know all kinds
of other stuff so you have to cross the
upper mantle mantle outer core in
accordion and so on so the crust is the
solid layer the mantle the upper and
lower mantle that's the magma layer
that's where you have molten rock at
very high temperatures it's so hot that
The Rock melts and that's the lava that
comes out of volcanoes so
and on top of that you have the the
solid crust which moves around so inside
the earth there is this entire ocean
of La of magma and the Earth's crust
essentially floats on that the the magma
is quite thick it's quite viscous right
it's like imagine the difference between
water and honey honey is much thicker
right so magma is even thicker than that
it's molten rock so the Earth's crust
floats around on that and you have all
these tectonic activity you know
tectonic plates that you have subduction
or tectonic plates that go under other
plates and some plates collide and all
that and it is all of this activity that
gives rise to volcanism as well as
earthquakes now the thing is that we
don't know much of what's Happening
underground we can't see it and the
deepest people have drilled underground
is just thin holes that go back about I
don't know 10 15 less than 15 kilometers
yeah and the the magma layer is way
below that
so we don't know what's happening under
the Earth surface we don't even know
what's under the oceans you know much of
it
so because we have almost no data about
what the conditions are in the magma
layer and all the tectonic activity
activity that's why we are unable to
predict earthquakes with any accuracy
now people use a variety of means you
know they observe the behavior of
animals of birds of fish and cats and
dogs and all that and uh typically what
happens is that before an earthquake
occurs there is some kind of activity
you know when it comes to birds and
animals they are able to hear sounds
that we can't hear for instance there is
this very popular euphemism called dog
whistle right so dog whistle is a
whistle that a that vibrates in the
ultra sound range it's what dogs can
hear but we can't hear even bats can
hear that
so when it comes to various uh
the tectonic activity there are certain
vibrations that occur which could be
either very low frequency vibrations or
high frequency vibrations most likely
this will be low frequency evaporations
and some animals and birds can sense
that they can detect it and when some
such thing happens it it looks like they
can actually tell that something bad is
going to happen like an earthquake and
they become uneasy and all that so if
you know what patterns of behavior look
for look for among animals and birds
then maybe you would know that maybe an
earthquake is impending
but that's a very uh rough and
approximate and inaccurate way of trying
to predict earthquakes ideally you would
want to know roughly within an hour's
time when an earthquake could happen you
know maybe like in in 24 hours there
could be another that sort of thing so
uh because we have so little data of
what's Happening below the Earth's
surface that's why it's so difficult to
predict earthquakes now let us look at
some other questions
um all right
uh Russia Ukraine is a
yeah that that is uh
okay let us what is what is this
question rtk in a conversation with
prakar
you talked about not promoting
fanaticism but what would you advise
those guys who've kind of become fanatic
against some communities about after
knowing the actual truth
uh look I obviously am against any form
of fanaticism any form of violence any
of that if some people have become
Fanatics against somebody else I would
say that uh we need to revisit and
rethink such uh attitudes
uh I'm not talking about any specific
Community or group of people or anything
I'm just saying making a general
statement that you know India is a
rising Nation India the past 1000 years
has been destroyed thoroughly right
especially in the past 300 years under
European occupation right and now India
is finally once again Rising
economically and geopolitically and
India if India is to rise all Indians
need to work together to do that if a
certain segment or segments of society
if certain segments of society like you
say are promoting or are becoming
fanatic or whatever I'm I'm not
mentioning I'm not supposed you know
pointing figures at anybody I'm just
saying that if
Suppose there are certain segments of
society one segment or five segments or
17 seconds whatever who become fanatic
and and that's going to be
counterproductive to India's rise what
needs to happen is everybody
irrespective of whatever ideology they
believe in or whatever belief system
they espouse or whatever religious
beliefs they have it doesn't matter they
are all Indians we all have to work
together we have to cooperate together
we have to come together and take the
nation forward together if you have all
this internal friction an internal
all these troubles then India is Never
Gonna uh go ahead and and become what
you know regain its its rightful place
in the world affairs and world history
so I would advise anybody who has I
don't know whatever like you say fanatic
uh mindset or whatever that uh you need
to uh we need to all work together right
we need to all work together we need to
all come together India is uh the oldest
and greatest civilization and no matter
what uh religion you belong to no matter
what ideology you believe in you we all
have the same ancestors we all have the
same Heritage we all have the same past
and we need to come together work
together cooperate together collaborate
together work harmoniously to take the
nation and our great civilization
forward once again and restore it to its
rightful place in the world order so
that's what I would say these Petty
small frictions you know
They don't serve any real purpose we
have to all work together and take the
nation forward
all right
um
let's see some other questions
why don't humans have eyes with red
irises an interesting question now uh
can you think of any mammal any animal
that has eyes with red irises
I cannot think of any if you look at
cats they've got yellow or green irises
you look at dogs dogs typically have
blue no sorry Brown irises mostly some
of them have blue irises some some
animals have heterochromia you know
irises of different colors so even some
humans have that and so on but I cannot
think of any animal
uh that has red irises
so iris color you know I would Brown
irises like it's like you can see and
and it's typically the result of
genetics it's the result of what you
have inherited from your ancestors
um so I I think it's it's because we
have evolved in a certain way and maybe
it was it was not uh
it was not something that helped to have
red irises perhaps I mean why don't
people have green irises some people do
why don't people have Violet irises for
instance yeah
so maybe it's it's not something that's
conducive to long-term
uh you know it's it's not a factor that
helps you
do better in the long run maybe so maybe
if such uh mutations happen that they
must have been weeded out in the
evolutionary game maybe yeah so uh
so it looks like as far as I can think I
cannot think of any animal that has red
irises so maybe that's a recessive trait
or a trait that is not very good for
long-term survival maybe that's the
reason why yeah
it's all about uh it's all about
Evolution it's all about survival of the
fittest so only those genetic traits and
physical traits are
propagated
across the generation so over a long
period of time that are actually
beneficial
to the survival and and the thriving of
the species those crates that don't
quite promote a better future for the
species uh they typically get weeded out
in the long term game of the of
evolution so that's what would have
happened I expect
all right
um
let us see some other questions
oh very interesting rabbits have red
eyes
interesting rabbits are well rabbits
yeah interesting do they have red eyes
maybe they do good for them but uh maybe
maybe
it's not something that is helpful to
them perhaps I don't know what it is
rabbits aren't quite the scariest
creature and not the you know the
they are they're
they typically serve as food for foxes
and wolves and cats and Eagles and all
that so yeah maybe
it's not really beneficial for them
uh Mr Gandhi says Mahatma Gandhi says am
I a bad leader sir your time is over so
it doesn't matter right we obviously
India needs to obviously uh revisit
its history
and revisit all the the careers of its
its major leaders the most influential
leaders the most consequential leaders
Mr Gandhi was certainly one of the most
consequential uh
political figures in India in the 20th
century no doubt about that he
did a lot to shape the kind of future in
the kind of course India took
politically and geopolitically and
economically and you know in a variety
of ways Mr Gandhi even today is
enormously influential because the
government still officially espouses uh
his various ideologies and viewpoints
and all that so uh it's something this
generation of Indians and future
Generations will have to do properly
they will have to revisit the history
not from the person from from the
perspective of Dogma what is Dogma Dogma
is the product and the result of other
people's thinking Dogma is when you just
accept somebody's perspective and make
it your own okay this person I like this
person I like his personality I like his
uh way of talking so I'm gonna believe
everything he says so it's when you stop
thinking critically and just accept
somebody else's opinion at face value
what needs to happen is we need to do
critical thinking it means you look at a
person's career a Leader's career and
examine their actions from the
perspective of logic from the
perspective of the natural interest and
who whom did those actions actually
serve then one of the major problems I
see among Indians is that they look at a
person's words oh but he wrote this he
wrote that and he said this and he has
so much writings in which he said so so
many nice things
Indians play so much emphasis on words
and Indians don't look at actions I
don't care what someone wrote
I want to see what were their that
person's actions and what were the
consequences of those actions whom did
those actions benefit and whom did those
actions serve
doesn't matter what the person said or
wrote or spoke
so please understand this this is part
of critical thinking ignore words ignore
statements just look at actions and that
is where I would say 99 of Indians fail
they only look at words so
so yeah Mr Gandhi uh we will indeed uh
revisit your career at that at various
appropriate times I'm sure lots of
historians will do that
and uh we I think it is it is
this generation of Indians and future
Generations generations of Indians who
will pass the verdict upon you whether
you are a good leader or a bad leader or
whatever it was right yeah
um
pratik shivastava what is your take on
German statement about Kashmir I am not
aware of any statement that Germany has
made but uh I will look it up
and maybe I will take such a question up
tomorrow
what we have to understand about Germany
is that Germany is a
it's a it's a big economy for sure it's
uh the economic and Industrial
Powerhouse essentially that drives the
economy of Europe but when it comes to
foreign policy when it comes to
geopolitics Germany
is an extension of the U.S Empire that's
what it is Germany is well to put it
bluntly a U.S visal state it doesn't
have an independent foreign policy it
the German Constitution was written by
essentially by Americans it was written
by proxy by German politicians who were
selected by the Victorious Americans
so it was made to look like the Germans
wrote their own Constitution but it was
actually all done by the Americans and
if there was a single word the Americans
did not like they would have it changed
and most likely such things happened so
the German Constitution wasn't written
by Americans Germany is essentially run
as per the um the way the Americans
wanted to be to be run German internal
security policy foreign policy all of
that it is 100 in line with uh the
national interest of the United States
and so uh any statements that Germany
makes regarding Kashmir or whatever you
we have to regard those as essentially
American statements now we know what the
Americans have been up to in the past
few days about Kashmir
uh this is just the beginning the United
States regards India as a long-term
rival right when you are a superpower
when you are an Empire you don't think
like the common man woman and child on
the street you have to think very
differently
and now I get this question often people
ask me that India is still a three point
something trillion dollar economy India
is not a big economy why would the
Americans be worried about India so
that's what people people don't grasp a
superpower an Empire doesn't look at
things from a week to week perspective
they think in terms of decades and
centuries in 20 years India is going to
be a major economy though if things go
the way they are going today and that is
something which doesn't will not go down
well with the US they don't want any
challenge to them in any way whatsoever
so they will start taking action now in
a variety of ways yeah so if there has
been a German statement on Kashmir I
would expect I've not seen it but I
would expect that it would be kind of
annoying to India and kind of you know
um kind of ambiguous and kind of uh
kind of pro-pakistan perhaps yeah that's
what I'm guessing
so if it is that then it is nothing but
the American policy of foreign policy at
plane right
uh okay
is the akhilesh says is the U.S taking
Revenge by giving f-16s to Pakistan as
we did not listen to them in Russia
Ukraine decisions it's not Revenge uh
yeah well they first of all they aren't
giving any new aircraft to Pakistan they
are offering Pakistan a roughly 450
million dollar uh upgrade package so
they are upgrading those uh F-16 fighter
planes to a newer configuration more
modern configuration which will make
those uh fighter planes more effective
in in any future war against India right
so the Americans are actively uh harming
India's national interest and they are
uh arming India's we could say one of
India's principal adversaries this is a
hostile action so why they're doing this
there are multiple reasons first of all
yeah they wanted India to fall in line
with them Ukraine Russia thing yeah they
wanted India to
they want India's foreign policy to be
the U.S foreign policy whatever the
Americans want India must do and since
India is not falling in line like a good
boy the Americans are now
or realizing that India is now becoming
a
you know beginning it's it's Ascent to
something which is a much larger role in
geopolitics India is already regarded by
many uh
experts who may not say this openly but
it's India is already regarded as a
great power
so there is one superpower there is an
aspiring superpower the one superpower
is the U.S
the aspiring superpower is China which
is kind of derailed the the aspirations
are right now kind of derailed and then
there are two great Powers these are
India and Russia
Nations like France and Germany these
are medium medium-sized Powers these are
not great Powers they look like great
powers from outside because they are
economically developed and
industrialized and all that but these
are
satellite states of the US
so you have the the one Empire the one
superpower us you have an aspiring
superpower which is China and then you
have two great Powers India and Russia
so uh so in the US wants to counter
balance India you the US will slowly
start ramping up its pressure on on
India that's how I see things going
and uh it's not only because India is
not Towing the American line and not
obeying American dictates on Russia it's
also because India is rising so even if
India were to fall in line with American
demands vis-a-vis it's it's foreign
policy the U.S would still
do such things like giving uh you know
like arming India's enemies because they
see India as a long-term threat they
don't want any Nation to rise and be a
threat in the future so yeah that's the
reason why
Lucario says your views on Ukraine
blowing up the Crimea Bridge yeah so
this uh incident happened there was a
massive uh
truck bomb explosion on the bridge okay
let's since we're talking about
a bridge we should take a look at the
bridge on the map
because we love the map
where's the map
here's the map
all right here it is so let's go okay
first of all let me Orient you all in
case you don't know where which
geographical region we talked about so
here we have India on the globe we all
know where it is now let's go westwards
westwards and then you have this region
the Black Sea north of Anatolia
present-day turkey
and then you have this peninsula over
here which is called the Crimean
Peninsula you have the city of
Sebastopol the Alta and Kirch and all
that so there's a bridge here
this is the bridge that that connects
the Russian Mainland with the peninsula
of Crimea
so this here is the Crimean bridge now
I'm not sure where the explosion
happened it would be somewhere along
along this bridge yeah it's a few
kilometers long maybe
uh
maybe about 10 12 13 14 kilometers long
there's an island in between which uh
fortifies a bridge
so there was an explosion very recently
less than 24 hours ago on the bridge a
truck bomb explosion suicide explosion
suicide bomber uh and parts of the
bridge have been damaged uh some of it
it looks like it is still serviceable so
it's not closed entirely to traffic but
yes it's been disrupted and the
significant repairs will have to be done
the pillars that hold up the bridge
haven't been destroyed but uh the the uh
top section uh on one side of the bridge
seems to have been damaged significantly
at a certain point and it will take some
time before it is restored to its uh
to the to its working condition now
obviously when something like this
happens we don't know who who has done
it but all the only question we have to
ask is who benefits from this and it's
clear that NATO benefits from this and
who's NATO's puppet it's Ukraine right
uh so most likely it would be some a
Ukrainian person who has done this or it
has been done at the behest of NATO by
Ukraine most likely I'm not saying I
know anything I know nothing I am I can
only see things as they happen and then
I can make deductions based on what
makes sense yeah so uh it certainly does
look like it's either Ukraine or NATO
and NATO would not get involved directly
in this when I speak about NATO
obviously it means the United States the
U.S will not get involved directly any
of in any of these things that's why
they're using proxies Ukraine is a proxy
for the U.S
so if this has been this has happened as
we know it has then it has been most
likely would have been done by by
Ukraine and on behalf of NATO and the
ukrainians uh I believe they've been
tweeting gleefully about what happened
sick burn or whatever they say they said
yeah one of their major Twitter accounts
and all so yeah this is something that
is par for the course in a war
gonna be the consequences of this there
is obviously going to be some kind of
Russian response to this the Russians uh
will not sit back and take this so there
could be other Russians have a variety
of means of responding to this and they
can chase they can choose a time and a
place of their of their choosing to
respond there could be conventional you
know missile attacks or or bombings
artery artillery attacks you could have
cyber attacks the Russians can they have
a variety of tools at their disposal
there could be AC metric uh response
responses to this yeah so we don't know
yet what the response is going to be
like now the bridge obviously they will
work
overnight to restore it to working
condition which may take a little bit of
time perhaps but yeah there most likely
will be some kind of retaliation from
Russia and let's see how that goes so
like I had said about a week or so ago
we are entering now the most dangerous
part of the Ukraine conflict yeah and
yeah let's take this question where is
it yeah
do you think Russia is losing so
yesterday I was in a hotel
uh I was in a hotel room and I had
nothing to do for an hour or so so I was
I had put the TV on you know hotel rooms
of TV so I put the TV on without the
sound and there are I was watching a
variety of Hindi news channels yeah
Indian news channels in Hindi and my
goodness look at the kind of propaganda
they're putting out I mean it's totally
one-sided and if you watch these news
channels you will get the feeling that
Russia is about to lose in the next half
hour yeah
so uh the Indian news channels are
essentially
solving as as they are echoing blindly
the Western viewpoint on what's
Happening
it's like Ukraine is is winning the war
Ukraine is destroying Russia the
Russians are falling back everywhere
everything is being destroyed in Ukraine
is winning and so that's the kind of
reporting I'm seeing on on on Indian
news media and even when it comes to the
very prominent two or three Indian
English news channels that that have
been covering the Ukraine conflict
once again it has been completely
one-sided coverage I I have nothing
against being biased everybody has some
bias of some kind whether it's uh
whether you know about it or not whether
you realize or not you are biased in
some way everybody is but the bias is
the the one-sided nature of the coverage
is very disappointing
so there are these news channels they
will send one or two reporters to cover
the conflict from the ground and if each
of these news channels sends their
reporters to the to the Ukrainian
territory so they are reporting from the
Ukrainian positions they are embedded
within the Ukrainian military
and obviously the coverage is going to
be entirely from Ukraine's perspective
why don't they for the sake of balance
also send a couple of reporters to the
Russian territory the Russian held
regions and embed them within the
Russian military so we can see two
perspectives and get a balanced coverage
none of them is doing this they're all
doing it from Ukraine's perspective from
NATO's perspective so the Indian media
is essentially
acting as a tool of NATO that's what
you're getting and if you watch these
news channels which I don't blame you
for then you will obviously get the
impression that Russia is losing now
obviously Russia is up against a very
powerful opponent NATO is all-powerful
the US is the only superpower in the
world they they actually are capable of
destroying Russia's conventional
military if they want to but obviously
it is extremely dangerous for them to
even contemplate that because of
Russia's disproportionately strong
non-conventional might right so that's
the uh brahmastra so to say that Russia
has and
uh so do I think Russia is losing if you
if I if I were to see all the news
coverage on on social media on the BBC
on the CNN on the American Media on the
you on the English-speaking media
worldwide or in the EU EU media if you
look at the news coverage they're all on
Twitter on Facebook wherever else you
will clearly get the feeling that Russia
is losing and they've been losing since
February 24.
and yet uh the truth is I'm sure
somewhat different from that so we don't
get to see the Russian perspective at
all so I
I don't think Russia is losing it I'm
not sure if they are winning so what's
happening the Russians are biding their
time because you know what
winter is coming they want winter to
come right Europe is facing an energy
crisis now somebody has blown up a
certain a major part of the North Street
stream pipeline that supplies gas to you
know to Europe so the Europeans are now
uh in a position to have to beg the
Americans for natural gas and whatever
and they will have to buy that that
energy at substantially higher prices
than what they would have acquired from
the Russians so Europe is now at
America's Mercy there is still one
portion of the node stream pipeline that
uh is undamaged and the Russians could
possibly uh send gas to Europe through
that there's also the other bullish uh
pipeline that they have or the the NATO
the NATO side has opened so they could
uh do it from there but yeah overall
what we are seeing is there is there is
there are signs of recession worldwide
in the U.S in Europe uh inflation is is
at a high uh various European currencies
have been hammered by the US dollar and
we are seeing the prospect of a very
harsh hard and cold winter you know you
could have power Cuts you could have uh
you know no no Heating in in homes in
India if you don't have any Heating in
your homes during winter especially in
the southern part of India you're okay
you know in Europe people can freeze to
death if that happens because Europe is
at much higher latitudes compared to
India so there are all these problems
and the Russians will want to wait till
winter and see how this winter how
Europe fares in this winter
so the Russians are playing the long
game they know that Europe is
hurtling into a crisis and Europe is the
opponent Europe is a proxy of the US the
one major power in NATO and in the
European Union is the US it's not
Germany it's not France it's not the UK
it's not Italy it's not Spain it's not
anybody else the only real power in
Europe in Western Europe is the US
and they now hold Europe hostage and
they want to enrich themselves at
Europe's cost so
so the Russians are going to buy that
time where Winter is Coming it's going
to be a very hard winter for Europe I
really feel sorry for the for the
innocent men women and children of
Europe the innocent citizens of Europe
who have done nothing to deserve this
yeah
I really feel sorry for them but this is
how the world has always been it's
always the innocent to suffer in war and
that's what we're going to see now so
the Russians from their side they're
going to bite their time let this drag
on let this go on into winter let winter
get over and then you may see some some
action happening and yeah so there's a
whole lot happening right now the Russia
Russia has annexed uh about one-fifth of
Ukraine right now and uh if the
Europeans if the ukrainians try to take
that back you could see you know
significant
uh escalations in the conflict so yeah
dangerous times right now very dangerous
times
all right
um
did I see something
okay nikhil Kumar says what are your
views on the new education policy 2020
uh what are My Views I think it's not
going to make much of a difference yeah
I'm sure there are small improvements
and small cosmetic changes and some
small non-cosmetic changes to maybe
they're gonna revise some of the
textbooks and have more accurate history
in there or but overall I think it's not
a big deal
and why do I say this so I have two or
three episodes on education I don't know
what numbers they are it's been a long
time
episode 30 32 31 somewhere there if you
want to see you can look at that in
which I've gone into detail into these
matters now ask yourselves my dear
friends this simple question
what is the purpose of Education
what's the purpose of Education
the answer is very simple the purpose of
education is to give the nation
highly skilled
highly capable confident young citizens
that's
the simple purpose of Education right it
education must Empower every boy and
every girl
to Live to Rise to their to the highest
of their potential to maximize their
potential is that what the education
system in India does no it gives the
nation confused and under confident
young adults who don't know who are
clueless right they have no confidence
they have no real skills the only skill
you learn in the education system is how
to pass exams how to memorize large
amounts of text to reproduce those texts
in the text in in those long essay type
questions
memorize stuff and pass exams that's the
only skill you acquire
you don't really acquire any other skill
in the education system
and by the time you're done with the
education system by the time you enter
the job market you have no real skills
so let's say you go into let's say an IT
job you're going to have to be trained
all over all over again the first three
to six months and then you will acquire
actual real world skills that will be of
any benefit to your to the company that
has hired you and that applies to any
field not only IIT anywhere else right
so the education system doesn't give you
any real skills and by the time you're
done you're confused you have no idea of
what what your strengths are you don't
even learn how to learn things it
doesn't teach you critical thinking it
doesn't so these are all the problems
you know it it produces young adults who
hate their own culture who are who who
feel ashamed of of their culture and
their history and their civilization and
of their of their ancestors yeah so it
is something that is greatly
counterproductive to to the nation to
the civilization and this new education
policy doesn't address any of that
as far as I can see it addresses now
none of the core issues
so that's my view about this we are
still far away from having a good
education system uh the education system
is colonial in nature it is a
continuation of the 19th century
colonial education system that the
British imposed upon India in order to
destroy India's culture and civilization
the Macaulay an education system and
that's what still continues in India
today
the new education policy does it undo
that does it uh thoroughly reform the
education system it does not so yeah it
doesn't excite me in any way whatsoever
it's it's like putting a Band-Aid on a
gunshot wound on a bullet wound right
so yeah so I I don't have any Great
Hopes for about this from this yeah
there are some benefits some positives
that maybe some textbooks will be
revised and you may get to learn more
accurate history and then there's the
problem of the multiple languages you to
study so you do study your mother tongue
you to study Hindi and you have to study
English three languages you should be
studying in only one language whatever
your mother tongue is and English needs
to be done away with at the earliest
possible time because it it perpetuates
mental colonization right so yeah and I
know lots of people disagree with me
well feel well free today free feel free
to disagree yeah but I am very clear
about this India needs to get rid of
English this colonial imposition Upon Us
in the India there's only one language
only one language that is appropriate
for being India's national language that
is sanskrit and here comes the hit which
is fine I don't care
so yeah the only language that can serve
as India's national language is India's
civilizational language is sanskrit we
can revive it in in just 20 years if we
want to if but I'm sure it's something
the government doesn't want to take up
right now because there are there are
other issues to to worry about
so I would like to see a two language
policy the national civilization
language would be Sanskrit and the the
other language should be your mother
tongue whatever it is whether it is
kannada whether it is Telugu whether
it's Tulu whether it's kashmiri whether
it's Assamese whether it is Marathi or
whatever odia whatever two languages
maximum you learn in a mother tongue and
you learn the civilization
civilizational language and let's get
rid of the language of the colonial
oppressors we don't need that people say
English is the language of Science and
progress and all that what utter
nonsense do you think uh the the do you
think the 20th century advances in
science were done in English who who do
you think inventor okay came up with
quantum mechanics the entire history the
first 20 30 years of quantum mechanics
are are all about the German language
and the French language mostly and some
Italian right none of it was done in
English so where where did the English
Advantage go and look at all the nations
that do really well in the world today
the top 10 economies how many of them
use English as their primary language
the Russians they became a superpower
did they do it through English no
it was Russian look at the French they
are proud of the French language all the
education all the science all the
technology is done in French look at the
Chinese do you think they force their
kids to to learn English no look at the
Japanese look at the Germans Indians
need to get over this mental
colonization the slave mindset that
English is great and we our languages
are inferior so it's all because of the
education system that people have this
mentality in this mindset and this
belief and I don't blame people for
instant beliefs so it will things will
only change Indians will become
confident
only when these core issues are
addressed so it's not been addressed
right now so I don't give a damn about
this goddamn new education policy 2020
it doesn't really do much not much small
small progress good okay thank you very
much really appreciate it but yeah not
enough not enough
so yeah that is one of my major
criticisms of this government
yeah all right let us yeah there you go
somebody has a great
sir sir thank you for pointing it
pointing it out like I said we are all
mentally colonized I am more comfortable
in English than in any of the Indian
languages do you see that is the state
we are in that's why this podcast is in
English and the other reason this
podcast isn't is in English is that I
want the world to know what what my
perspective is and what India's position
is
and what what is right for India and
unfortunately today the language of the
world is English and the language if I
if I start speaking in Hindi half my
audience even the Indian audience will
not will possibly not be able to
understand me so thank you for pointing
it out sir uh very astute observation
I'm not trying to make fun of you at all
sir but yeah it is unfortunately this is
where we are today
because of the education system let's
say I start doing the podcast in
Sanskrit will you understand what I'm
saying
so there's no point to
pointing this out because it doesn't
help anybody sir
yeah there you go if we all if we get
rid of English won't we be cut off from
the rest of the world is China cut off
from the rest of the world is Japan cut
off from the rest of the world is France
cut off from the rest of the world does
the Chinese foreign minister give give
his his uh Communications in English
does the Ministry of Foreign office or
the any Ministry in China give addresses
and give communicate communicates in
English does the French President go and
speak to everybody in English
what what this is the problem and I
don't blame this person who has put put
this comment this is what we have we
have been made to believe that without
English we are isolated we are done we
have finished
that is not the case Any self-respecting
Nation will have its education system in
its own native language whether it is
the one civilization language or
whatever the mother tongue is in in case
of these small countries like France and
Germany that's that's only one language
major language so they have their
education system in that language you go
to study in Germany you're going to have
to learn German good do you know that
you go to Sweden you want to study there
you're gonna have to learn Swedish
they will not allow you to study in
English
so yeah you you get rid of English you
will not be cut off from the rest of the
world the world will respect you more
and that's what we don't get because
this is the kind of brainwashing that's
done to us done to us through the
education systems you know in the Indian
education system
what sort of kid is considered to be an
intelligent kid
a kid who speaks good English see how
good his or her English is they're so
intelligent
you have a good you know uh UK like
accent good God that's that's the sign
of intelligence not how well you
understand things how well you analyze
things not your critical thinking
ability not your knowledge the accent in
which you speak English that is what
matters so this is the kind of mental
colonization we have all been subjected
to
so I don't blame people for having these
beliefs these attitudes it is not your
fault my dear friends
right but it is something that needs to
be addressed and it is not for you and
me and for the common people of India to
address this the government needs to get
its act together but I understand why
they're not doing it right now you you
look at the history of the past few
years
any major change the government tries to
to make it is met with Incredible
incredible backlash
sometimes it comes from within the
government sometimes it comes from
various political parties that could or
could not may or may not have foreign
funding
uh the academic system the so-called
civil society and then the media and the
media brainwashes you all into believing
various things and then obviously your
favorite influencers whoever they are
um I'm sure there are many
so any kind of Reform any major reform
the government attempts to do it invites
an enormous backlash from coordinated
backlash from the media from the
Academia from the intelligence Shia from
the from the so-called intellectuals
from from a foreign media from from
politicians from various political
parties all coordinated together in and
they try to make it look like the
government is trying to destroy the
country
yeah so that's why the government is
currently not trying to uh reform the
education system too much because it's
it's it's going to be a very long and
dirty fight and there are bigger
problems to address right now so yeah I
get it but yeah it kind of it's still
you know disappoints me
but I I do understand why it is the way
it is right now so yeah this mental
conversation colonization is going to
continue enjoy
all right
um
when everybody speaks a language then
all the content will be in that language
yeah so if we could
um
so if we could all be educated in just
our mother tongue and the national law
civilization language then the bridge
language the connecting language will
once again be our civilization language
which is sanskrit I always Advocate
Sanskrit because it is the only language
that makes sense it is the language that
that uh
that brought not only the Indian
subcontinent together but also most of
Asia Eastern Asia you know Java Sumatra
Indonesia Philippines Cambodia Laos
Vietnam Korea Japan China all of that
there was one civilization language in
the entire extended Indo sphere Sanskrit
so I would say that we should have a two
language policy every child should learn
only two languages one is your mother
tongue your primary your main education
should be in your mother tongue because
you understand any concept much better
in your mother tongue then as opposed to
First Learning a foreign language and
then trying to learn Concepts through
that foreign language
and Sanskrit is our real mother tongue
it is it's a language that gives us most
of our vocabulary in most Indian
languages yeah so it's also a language
that will be very easy to learn so one
should have to uh we should have a two
language policy and the link language
the bridge language the civilization
language so if everybody speaks that
then all the content will be in that
language that language will see a
Revival and if you revive Sanskrit you
are Reviving Indian civilization so yeah
I would like to say that happen but it's
not going to happen anytime soon
unfortunately
um
all right uh let's see some other
questions
who according to you is going to won the
24 elections I I don't know I cannot see
the future I hope that the current
government will
uh remain in power because it's the only
government that makes sense and that's
the only government that is capable of
it taking India forward am I biased yes
I'm biased I'm biased in favor of India
I want India to do well and I don't see
any other political party
taking India forward in the right
direction yeah so I am biased I'm
perfectly clear about that and I make no
apologies for that I hope the BJP and Mr
Modi win the 24 elections
um
Tamil I have the greatest of love and
respect for Tamil right so yes one
should cherish Tamil one should promote
Tamil I would say that other Indians
even those who are non-tamil should
learn Tamil as as they should learn
other languages too uh kannada Telugu
beautiful languages Tulu I mean nobody
speaks about Tulu what about odia why is
odia neglected yeah why is odia
neglected why doesn't anybody want to
learn Assamese why doesn't anybody want
to learn manipuri and so on we should
cherish all our languages and I'm sick
and tired of certain people
trying to certain certain people having
this supremacist attitude that my
language is superior and all other
languages some some people a small
minority of people have such attitudes
so like I said we need to stop fighting
amongst each other we are one people we
are one civilization we need to
cooperate we have to work together
support each other stop fighting and
take the nation and the civilization
forward please let's do that
um
Tushar says any specific reason for not
cutting your hair yeah and no specific
reason uh the last time I had a haircut
was uh sometime in 2019 and then I got
myself a crew cut there's a video on
this channel in which I'm I give an
address
um during the book release it was a book
released by uh two authors uh Major
General GD bakshi and srikant talageri
so I gave a keynote address about
an introduction to the Aryan Invasion
Theory and if you see me there I have a
crew cut you know the military cut very
short hair uh haircut so that was 2019
that's the last time I had a haircut and
after that you had we know what happened
the pandemic happened and all so uh so
yeah I just let it grow and yeah a week
or so ago I chopped off some of it
because it was getting way too long so I
just did it myself I took a pair of
scissors and snipped done
uh so that's it there's no real reason I
I there have been times when I've kept
my hair long and this is one of those
times there is no specific reason there
is no religious reason or ideological
reason or scientific reason it's just
something that happened and I'm I'm good
with that I'm happy with that no issues
um
all right let's see
Mr Giga chat of India what are your
views on those who say that you are
funded by Modi me
I wish I wish
I wish I was funded by somebody please
if somebody wants to fund me please fund
me but I will not change my views and my
pronouncements My Views will always
remain independent
if somebody were to fund me I would
invite that but I will uh not obviously
change the way I talk what I say yeah so
yeah if people want to say that feel
free to say whatever you want it's a
free Nation it's a free country
you have freedom of expression say
whatever you want unfortunately I'm not
funded by anybody which is
sad sad life yeah sad
all right
let us see other questions
says your take what's your take on the
recent Indian defense deal signed for
250 million dollars do you think it
would be a revolution for the Indian
economy I believe India is uh selling
some military equipment uh to uh to to
Armenia not to Azerbaijan Azerbaijan is
the bad guy out here
uh they are the ones who are
doing all kinds of terrible things
against the Armenians Azerbaijan is a
proxy of Turkey
yeah so yeah India is supporting Armenia
in this matter and India is sending 250
million dollars worth of Defense
equipment uh uh yeah to Armenia so it's
a good thing is this a revolution for
the Indian economy not quite above 250
million dollars is not a whole lot of
money from from a national perspective
for you or me it's it's a whole lot of
money yeah but from a national
perspective it's a small amount of money
but it's a good uh it's a good sign we
are supporting the right Nation
it's a geopolitical statement we're
making it's it's a statement of
principle we're making
and obviously it uh tells the world that
we are now a defense manufacturer we we
uh
our defense equipment is is good and
there are buyers for that so it's it's a
good start I would like to see India
become a major defense exporter
obviously we don't want to fund Wars and
all that when it comes to uh turning
defense into a major industry it's like
the Americans have done they've been
funding Wars worldwide
for the past Century or so nearly
so I don't I don't want that to happen
but India should definitely become
self-sufficient entirely uh in defense
and certain we can certainly uh help out
uh like-minded nations with their
defense needs when this happens so it's
a very good step it's not yet a
revolution but eventually one could see
a major defense deals happening in the
future maybe in a decade or so I it
should happen we should reach that that
stage as soon as possible that's what I
would say
all right
yeah
every session there has to be something
about taking back POG right
patience patience
so uh pokojk it's on some parts of uh of
Kashmir jamun Kashmir which are
currently temporarily occupied by
Pakistan it's a temporary phase you know
um
uh is India waiting for a wrong move
from Pakistan to take back P okay India
is not currently looking at Pok as far
as I can as far as I can deduce
um there are what needs to happen with
Pakistan is
we don't want to take back PUK without
Pakistan itself disintegrating so once
again let me preface this by saying that
I have no ill feeling for the innocent
civilians of Pakistan the men women and
children they are the same people as us
they have the same answers to the same
Heritage the same history they are our
blood they're our brothers and sisters I
don't wish them anything bad but
Pakistan as a nation is a terrorist
state
no two ways about that Pakistan is a
terrorist Nation the Pakistan Army is a
terrorist organization and Pakistan
needs to be uh
balkanized for peace to Prevail in the
entire subcontinent even the Iranians
will be happy with it the Afghans will
be happy with it and India needs this to
happen for for us to have peace finally
once and for all on the Western border
it will also ensure that other larger
Nations cannot use Pakistan as a stick
to beat Pakistan to beat India and
Afghanistan and possibly even Iran with
right so Pakistan is is a temporary
Nation created out of convenience out of
geopolitical interests of the
Anglo-Saxon Empire
so for Pok to be resolved essentially we
need Pakistan to uh
to a breakup into its constituent parts
we would like to see a free Balochistan
we would like to see a free Sindh a free
Pakistani Pakistani Punjab
we would like to see
um
and uh the Northwest Frontier Province
they would like to see that reintegrated
with Afghanistan because that's the uh
that's what the person people desire
right it's the major bone of contention
between Afghanistan and Pakistan so that
that should happen and when when these
these things happen it is but naturally
that the temporarily occupied the pojk
will revert to India where it has always
belonged for thousands of years
um so yeah we need to work together for
this to happen yeah what can we do we
can contribute to the Indian economy and
and bolts to the Indian economy and as
the economy grows the government will
have more options and more options on
the table you know more tools at its
disposal
so yeah this needs to happen and I don't
see Pakistan lasting more than 10 years
I once again let me say I have nothing
against the people of Pakistan I wish
them well I wish them prosperity and
happiness for them and their in the
children and the future Generations
nothing against them and if this
disintegration this organization happens
it should happen hopefully peacefully
without any without any any significant
damage yeah that's what one hopes and
um this is obviously also tied to the
Tibet issue because Tibet obviously is
also temporarily occupied by China we
would like to see Tibet free again yeah
so yeah all these issues are inter
linked and interrelated uh so yes India
needs to keep this in mind as its
long-term goals and it will happen
sooner or later hopefully sooner
all right
Divya says why isn't India focusing on
health and education so we have the new
education policy which uh does which
which does implement some reforms some
small reforms that don't really address
the core issues of mental colonization
of the colonial system remaining and all
that like I said just a while ago India
is focusing on education to that extent
on on reforming the education to a small
extent
I think most kids if not all kids have
access to education today yeah uh when
it comes to health India I think India
has done reasonably well actually when
it comes to health India has been able
to um
get over the the coronavirus crisis yeah
India has done way better than other
nations in in the speed of
implementation of the vaccination we
developed our own vaccines we vaccinated
uh most all all eligible adults with two
doses of the vaccine we did that very
efficiently the West was waiting for
millions of Indians to die and they were
so disappointed when nothing of that
sort happened right uh all the stories
they were putting out in the media of
the the coronavirus pandemic actually
being much worse than what it looks like
in India and millions of Indians will
die all of those stories have been
quietly set aside and pushed under the
carpet brushed into the carpet now
because none of that happened that is
incredible uh
that's that's a that's an incredibly
excellent performance by the government
and when it comes to other health issues
India is still you know a very it's
India is still a developing Nation uh
and uh we obviously have the health
benefits that people get the Pradhan
mantri uh something or the other yojana
or whatever I don't remember the name I
I apologize for not remembering the name
but I think everybody gets gets uh
health insurance coverage at a very
nominal cost so the intention is there
yes and as India gets more prosperous as
the economy gets better I expect that
the quality of healthcare will also
improve I have said this not in a long
time but I've said this in the past that
eventually any civilized society should
give completely free education and
completely free health care to its
citizens that's how it was in Ancient
India education was 100 free it was
entirely subsidized by the state by the
kings and queens and the Emperors who
were whoever it was and so was
Healthcare even after 1947 for some time
in some so-called princely States
Healthcare was still given to Citizens
for free
that's no longer the case Healthcare has
now been turned into an industry when
you turn something into an industry they
will want to maximize the amount of
money they can extract out of each
patient and that's why we have all these
problems today so yeah these things need
to be taken care of but we unfortunately
will not be able to do this for the next
10 20 years it will be slow progress but
I do things that the government of India
is indeed focusing on health and
education
once the economy Rises there will be
more money to invest in these things and
hopefully things will change for the
better I think things are already
improving to a certain extent and the
coronavirus virus pandemic the way the
government dealt with that was better
than 99 of the world better than what
the Americans did way better than what
the Chinese did and way better than what
Europe did so I think India was a
Shining Light in the entire world when
it comes when it comes to handling the
coronavirus pandemic that horrible
crisis that lasted two years in India
not only did uh
take care of its own citizens and in
India gave the ones who had lost their
jobs and all various benefits you know
food grains at a very discounted price
and all that they did everything they
could the government
India also tried to support as many
other nations as possible by by sending
vaccines no other nation has shown this
sort of leadership so let us uh not
forget these things I think we have a
very capable government and a very
capable prime minister uh with us right
now we are very fortunate to have this
very often what happens is that you
don't realize what you have on after
until after it's gone so I for one do
I'm very grateful that we have a very
capable government and a very capable
prime minister and yeah we are focusing
on these things Maybe not maybe not to
the extent that we all would like we
would all like the the Health Care
system to be like the way it is in the
U.S or Canada or whatever actually the
U.S Healthcare System is terrible it's
extremely extremely
um uh expensive yeah
anyway so yeah that's where we are today
um
all right let's see what other questions
we have I said
the US has sent vaccines as well and we
have refused those vaccines because
those are mRNA vaccines we have no idea
what what what is the deal with that and
and initially they refused to send India
raw materials for making Indian vaccines
they said America first that's what Mr
Biden said and that was a very good
thing it could have been it could have
been a disaster for India because the
Americans were refusing to send India
the raw materials for making vaccines
for making various pet equipment and all
that it was actually a boon in Disguise
today India is able to manufacture all
of these things on its own so the
Americans use everything as Leverage
so they must have sent vaccines here or
there those vaccines are very dodgy
vaccines I don't trust those vaccines
the Pfizer vaccine and now all the truth
is coming out you know the side effects
and all the complications and whatnot
I'll not go into that yeah but we know
what what the what what happened as a
consequence of the of those vaccines the
most efficacious and efficient vaccine
in the whole world when it comes to the
coronavirus is the Indian vaccine
and none of the western journalists and
observers want to speak about this but
the data is out there the Chinese
vaccine cyanovax is terrible less than
33 efficiency maybe in less than 12
percent efficiency well I if I'm
mistaken uh the the
moderna vaccine in the Pfizer vaccine
good God the Pfizer is the worst of the
lot even worse than final act so yeah we
don't need I mean
they may have sent vaccines to certain
Nations they wanted India to give
approval to their vaccines India they
refused to do that and I'm so glad we
did that
right
yes messenger RNA and all that so yeah
so what Bobby said is indeed true that
the Americans did send vaccines to some
people but those vaccines I'm so glad
India did not accept them and India did
not in India refused to certify those
vaccines
all right
um
okay what else do we have
let us see
samath says do you think scientific
progress can happen without Wars if no
any reason behind that theme
scientific progress does happen because
of the Technologies we need to uh create
for Warfare a lot of scientific
development happens with that for
instance in the 20th century uh the
nuclear race was there that very rapidly
developed all kinds of nuclear
technologies which have uh civilian
applications as well nuclear power if
you look at France more than 30 percent
of their electricity is generated from
nuclear power so yeah but they first the
Americans first designed the very first
nuclear reactor for making a bomb so
that that's a very good example and then
once again you had the space race
the Russians took the lead the Americans
wanted to catch up the Americans were
terrified the Russians would put nukes
in space on satellites and so on so this
actually had a military Dimension the oh
the entire reason why the Space Race
happened was that they were worried
about the militarization of this
technology and these Technologies are
very clear military Dimensions these are
primarily military Technologies and yet
today we have satellites we have
communication satellites without which
this telecast would not happen and so on
saw a lot of scientific progress happens
because of the technologies that one has
to develop for military purposes that is
indeed true we humans are a war-like
violent aggressive species that's what
we are and so in it it is also the case
with our closest relatives the
chimpanzees these are also very violent
just like us that's just the way we are
we are inherently a violent species of
the the entire history of humanity is
essentially a history of Wars It's a
history of various great leaders
powerful leaders good or bad doesn't
matter powerful leaders and the wars
they waged and all historical change has
mainly happened through Wars mainly
mainly so yeah and that obviously has
driven a whole lot of scientific
progress one would like to see
scientific progress without war and one
did see such such phases of human
history especially in India we have the
entire Saraswati Hindu phase of Indian
history which seems to have had no war
whatsoever we have archaeologists have
looked very assiduously very hard for
for evidence of warfare they found none
whatsoever yeah so we had this you
almost utopian phase of history in which
you have like two three thousand years
of History where you don't find any
evidence of warfare of battles of any
such thing and there was a whole lot of
scientific and technological progress in
the in the in the time so ancient India
during the Saraswati Hindu phase was the
most scientifically and technologically
advanced civilization of all time right
uh and we see that in the archaeological
record there was dentistry seven eight
thousand years before today the the
ports and the harbors of that time they
compare favorably to Ports and harbors
in Modern India where aircraft carriers
dock right and obviously you had uh and
a whole lot more which I have spoken
about so many times so that was a phase
of human history where you had a huge
amount of scientific progress
technological progress without Warfare I
mean as far as we know there was no
Warfare we know that Indians did have
uh military strength at the time and
there is an instance of Indian
involvement in a foreign war during the
Sarasota time which was the war between
ramush of akkad The Arcadian Empire and
our neighbors the marhashi kingdom which
is present-day Iran Southern Iran
so India sent troops to the aid of the
maharashi Kingdom in their conflict with
the Acadian Empire so that is something
that is part of the historical record so
even though our civilization was
entirely peaceful there is no evidence
of War but we did have military strength
and we did participate in geopolitics
beyond the Indian subcontinent so yeah
that's how it is I think progress
technological progress scientific
progress essentially much of it is
driven by military requirements and
needs and exigencies and that's just how
it is
but one can certainly have progress
without Wars but typically not that's
not happened
I don't know what the name is what is
your book collection I have a whole lot
of books my dear friends
um I've got two bookshelves here and I
have a whole lot more I have way too
many books than than most people could
handle I have read more books than I
have bought and I have and I buy more
books than I can possibly read so yeah
uh do you believe the humans are the
future aliens completely evolved there
is no such thing as completely evolved
no matter what stage of evolution you
are in right now you're gonna always
keep on evolving in the future so in
another 100 000 years if you still if
you last that long you will have a whole
different kind of evolution possibly
based on what uh
what situations and circumstances your
species encounters right so if Humanity
in the future becomes a space-faring
species then we could evolve differently
over maybe a period of half a million
years 200 300 400 500 000 years yeah
so Evolution never stops there is no
such thing as completely evolved and
this is perfect that's not the case ever
evolution is a constant process as long
as a species exists it keeps evolving
the evolution doesn't happen week upon
week it happens
Millennium it doesn't even happen over
periods of thousands of years evolution
is visible only over periods of hundreds
of thousands of years yeah so uh yeah if
Humanity becomes a space-faring species
we could be future aliens like when we
think of aliens we think of these beings
that uh travel across Interstellar space
yeah so in the future Humanity could be
one of those species that travels across
into the Stellar space and settles down
in planets or Star systems beyond our
own
but we will never be completely evolved
the evolution is a constant process it
never stops
okay
um
let's see other questions
[Music]
um what do we have this
visual sparseness
it's the first time in my entire life
that I've come across this term
visual visual visual sparseness what's
that
sparseness means frugality moderation
less than moderation visual I'm
sorry not quite sure what this is Sir
not quite sure
uh yes did you ever have a mental
breakdown unfortunately no I mean
unfortunately no I've never had one of
those yeah
never had one of those
thankfully yes
uh green snake says contribution of
rajputs and Sikhism I think
when it comes to the the sick people
most of most of them not all obviously
but most of them are either jats or
rajputs right
uh Sikhism emerged as as opposition to
foreign oppression and colonization
typically mostly by the Turks entirely
by the Turks it uh Sikhism the the sikhi
not Sikhism
uh the Sikh religion
emerged as
as
a means of opposing and fighting back
against turkic brutality and oppression
and occupation and colonization of India
right and obviously it was a martial way
of life a militaristic way of life
and I think many of the original six
were rajputs so when we speak about a
person who is sick it's not an ethnicity
or a race right it anybody can be a sick
even even a European can become a Seeker
whatever so uh
many of the original six and many of the
presentations are also of rajput origin
right so that's what I can say about
this
okay
says can you tell us why you the U.S is
not joining the Ukraine war when you can
get somebody else to fight and die for
you why would you get involved
why would you do that why would you send
your own people to fight and die when
you can send somebody else to do it for
you so that's what we call a proxy war
right when you had the pakistanis uh
funding terrorism in India
they were not sending their own soldiers
so there was plausible deniability that
we are not involved in this it's this is
just some terrorism Freedom Fighters
so-called Freedom Fighters who are doing
this it's your internal Law and Order
issue right so the pakistanis could have
this plausible deniability
and we all know who was funding the
pakistanis finance in the pakistanis it
was the Americans
so it was a two you know proxy were at
two levels the pakistanis were using
terrorists as proxies and the Americans
were using Pakistan as a proxy to to
bleed India
so when you can do when you have such a
wonderful convenient Arrangement why
would you send your own people to to
fight and die
so the Americans want to technically
stay out of the war
so they are using Ukraine to fight
Russia and they will fight this war
until the last Ukrainian can fight so
yeah that's the reason why plausible
deniability and you can get your
whatever you want done without losing
any of your own people or your own
equipment and you have plausible
deniability right
lost contact with Mongolian is it true I
believe Mongolian has finally run out of
fuel of energy the battery or whatever
I'm not sure I heard about this so This
mission was designed to to last six
months
the when was the mission launched
manglion 2014 2015 I think 2014 perhaps
let me quickly check Mongolian
m-a-n-g-a-l-y-a-a and mango yam
so yes it was launched in it it started
orbiting the planet Mars in September
2014. let me just put this on the screen
what on Earth not this
one second sorry about that let me put
the Google search on the screen
the bare basic facts
so uh this was orbiting Mars since 24
September 2014. and uh
yeah so what happened is that it's it's
finally run out of energy its batteries
must have died out or whatever so it was
designed to last for six months but it
lasted more than eight years it's an
incredible achievement and that too on a
shoestring budget so yeah I think it has
finally lost contact with the satellite
and that's just how things go eventually
all satellites run out of
uh battery power energy whatever it is
and one loses contact with them so yeah
we would like to see more such missions
in the future right uh we have a
chandrayaan coming up soon and then we
have a human space flight program that
India is going to be launching I think
in the next within the next couple of
years
we will launch actual Indian astronauts
into space that's going to happen soon
so very excited for that I think there
is a shukrian to a mission uh a mission
to a spacecraft that will be sent in
orbit around Venus I believe so
interesting science coming up there is
the Aditya thing also which is a solar
Observatory that India is going to be
launching into space
so pretty interesting uh
missions coming up in the future so yeah
Mongolian is obviously something that is
going to lie last only a specific amount
of time it exceeded those Expectations
by a huge amount which is a great uh
performance and a great result for us
um
Barney says regarding Tibet I heard that
the Chinese Communist Party are planting
Han Chinese in Tibet to change
demography if so many years are passed
will Tibet really want freedom this is
something they've been doing since the
very beginning since the 1950s they have
been changing the demographics of Tibet
today I believe there are more Han
Chinese in Tibet than actual Tibetans
they have completely changed the
demography of Tibet this is something
they've done on purpose deliberately so
that
the aspirations of the Tibetan people
will be destroyed forever so if so many
years have elapsed will Tibet still
really want freedom it still wants
Freedom the land belongs to the Tibetan
people to the indigenous people not to
the Han Chinese
so whenever Tibet is liberated the Han
Chinese will have to leave the place
and yeah that's that's I mean that's
what the one will have to respect the
will and the opinion of the Tibetan
people they are the ones who should
decide what happens in their own land
and most likely I mean it would only be
fair and just for the people who have
been planted over them to be sent back
to the Homeland which is which is China
type so yeah if
if you have so many Chinese then it
really complicates matters and that is
precisely why they've been sent there
when it comes to Pakistan Kashmir they
have been changing the pakistanis have
been changing the demographics over
there also
there have been uh
they have been um
settling
non-kashmiris in the place for a very
long time to ensure that the kashmiri
people will not have a say in what
happens in their own Homeland that's
what the pakistanis have been doing so
this is something that uh people that
various
uh authoritarian regimes do in order to
crush the aspirations
of of various peoples
So eventually one hopes that uh whether
it is Pakistan Kashmir or whether it's
Tibet these places and the people of
these places will see True Justice and
most of it much of it will will depend
on what India does in the next in the
coming years
all right let's see something else
what if all the Central Asian countries
reunite and form a union like the EU
well
um what what purpose will it serve
all the Central Asian Nations see what
are the centralization names uh
Tajikistan Uzbekistan
Kyrgyzstan Turkmenistan Azerbaijan and
so on and so forth uh we also have a
Chinese occupied xinjiang which is East
turkistan that's what some people call
it
uh these nations are all over all you
could say turkic in culture but
ethnically they they have differences
the caregivers people are not the same
as the Uzbek people and those big people
are not the same as the turkmen people
so once again let's take a look at the
uh map and understand what region we are
referring to
so let's take a look at the globe we are
talking about Central Asia so we
typically talk about the erstwhile re
the the region that was uh there was in
the past called uttara mudra
uttarakuru was the the eastern part of
Central Asia present day temporarily
Chinese occupied xinjiang
and uttar mother was this entire region
over here which is north of gandar which
essentially is Tajikistan Turkmenistan
Uzbekistan Kazakhstan Kyrgyzstan
and you could also perhaps include
Azerbaijan that most likely not even
though Azerbaijan is indeed turkic when
it comes to Tajikistan Tajikistan is not
a turkic land it's not a turkey country
the tajiks are essentially uh an Iranian
indo-iranian people and there are uh
there is a small tajik a certain not
small but a small moderate tajik
minority in Afghanistan as well in
Northern Afghanistan
so these nations I don't see any reason
why they would would want to unite and
former Union like the EU the EU is a
union that has been formed by the
Americans to Serve American geopolitical
interests right so I there's no real
reason for these Central Asian countries
to unite and I'm not sure what purpose
it would serve them all yeah so it's
something that will most likely not
happen right
okay
um
tarun khatri says your views on
adipurush I assume you're referring to
the movie that is going to be released
sometime in the future
if that's what you're referring to I I
did indeed unfortunately watch the
trailer
and it was
it was ghastly absolutely ghastly and
and lots of people have remarked about
this uh one of these actors he plays the
role of ravan who's the what's his name
one of the khans he doesn't look like
ravan he looks like somebody was saying
like a turkic Invader of India yeah
looks like that no Saif Ali Khan right
uh the son of the cricketer uh so yeah
Saif Ali Khan he looks like a turkic
Invader he doesn't look like ravan and
there is a scene in which he's
he's sitting on a back a giant vampire
bat and flying around so it's it's
something I don't know what weird
inspiration they've got from what places
some of it seems to be inspired from the
story of Dracula some of it seems to be
inspired from The Lord of the Rings some
of it seems to be inspired from The Game
of Thrones it's just it's a mishmash of
things that are they don't that don't
belong together and then the divanaras
are portrayed as monkeys and the the
their portrait the way the monkeys were
portrayed in the Planet of the Apes
movie series you know
so yeah they've simply blindly aped and
copied various disparate sources that
they have been inspired from and I'm not
sure it's going if if
it's going to be true to the story of
sriram uh the person who plays Lord Rama
he's a very buff guy I don't remember
the name of the actor but he looks angry
in every scene he looks angry and
Furious in everything Lord Ram was not
an angry man
he he
Lord Ram was an equanimous person he was
a calm person he fought a righteous War
but he was not an angry man it's wrong
to portray him as an angry person
there's a guy who's constantly angry but
that's the kind of uh
feeling I got from seeing the trailer of
a brief trailer that Lord Rama's
portrait as an angry person
so um
you know in a way it's good that
Bollywood is now being forced against
its will
to uh to make movies about Indian
history and the Indian Indian cultural
and religious themes in a way it's good
but they are doing a terrible job job of
do of it so yeah that's the that's the
conundrum that we are facing I think it
is moving it is the film industry
further down south in the southern parts
of India where there is a Telugu
industry or the various other interests
they are doing a far better job thus far
in in
in uh respecting and portraying Indian
culture and history so uh yeah that's
the impression I got about this movie
ADI purush it looked like a terribly
made movie or maybe they make they could
make some improvements I don't know a
lot of it is CGI and uh it's not
something that makes me want to watch it
yeah so that's my views on based on the
little that I've seen thus far
uh um
okay
um I think that's the question I just
answered
okay Shaheen says in the upcoming two
years will China attack India
what will our government do in that case
to combat Chinese influence
so the Chinese could indeed be tempted
to to possibly
attack India so why in the next two
years that's the question right so it's
a very strange situation that we are in
whether it is China whether it's
Pakistan or whether it's the U.S
when it comes to India they have the
same views and same opinion they don't
want in their eyes
and they don't want this government the
government of Mr Modi to stay in power
they would all whether it's China
Pakistan or the us all three of them
would like to see a much weaker
government come to power they would like
to see Mr Modi lose the 2024 election
and one of the ways of achieving such an
objective is to inflict a military
defeat on India which the people of
India you all would see as a humiliation
and a failure of the government right
and then the government would lose the
next election and great victory for the
Chinese and the Americans in the
pakistanis
so because of that the Chinese could
indeed be tempted to
indulge in some kind of ridiculously
stupid military base adventure with
India possibly in the Siliguri region
possibly somewhere else you know try to
quickly grab some territory and hold on
to it the and thus uh inflicted defeat
and the humiliation on India that could
be the Temptation that is something that
Mr Xi Jinping would have at the back of
his mind you know they would be biding
his time and looking for a good
opportunity for to do that the problem
is that India is now Rising India's
economy is getting stronger India is
strengthening its military
infrastructure its border infrastructure
overall India is looking up so I'm not
sure if they will be able to find a good
time to do that the problem is that if
they cross India's red lines there it
could invite very serious retaliation
from India you know because when it
comes to Chinese positions in Tibet
let's let's take a look at the map
so China occupies Tibet temporarily
right now for now they do it and they
have a variety of military bases in
infrastructure and Air Force bases in
Tibet they have built lots of roads they
have uh you know all kinds of military
installations in this region especially
in the Border areas around India
the problem for the Chinese is that
their aircraft if they take off from
such a high altitude they will be able
to carry less Fuel and less weaponry
and just a few hundred kilometers away
if Indian aircraft take off from the
arunachal Pradesh region or wherever
else Assam region or whatever we are
taking off essentially from much lower
close close much closer to sea level
than anywhere in Tibet so Indian
aircraft can carry much more a much
larger load of weapons and fuel so
that's an advantage India has over there
and of course all the Chinese positions
military positions are very thoroughly
exposed in this region because there are
no forests here there's nowhere to hide
the only place to hide is between is in
between the very various Crags and The
Valleys in the mountains and yet India
has satellites that that keep an eye on
everything the Chinese are doing
and India has missiles that can actually
you know
that can go up a mountain and then go
down a mountain at a 70 degree angle the
the brahmos missile so that's the kind
of Advantage India has that's the kind
of missile that India has that the
Chinese don't have so it's a it's quite
possible for India to take out a
significant portion of the Chinese
military infrastructure in a in a series
of very rapid missile strikes yeah so
I'm not sure if it makes sense for the
for the Chinese to indulge in a military
misadventure with India and when it
comes to Mountain Warfare technology
doesn't play that much of a role as
compared to to actual human uh capital
in quality you know
in Mountain Warfare the the quality of
his soldiers often is more important
than the kind of ammunition and the kind
of Technology they're using of course
technology is also important but when it
comes to hand to hand combat and all the
Chinese aren't quite so good you know
you may have seen certain reports and
certain videos of Chinese trying to
fight Indians and all their Kung Fu and
all it is of no use when they're
fighting Indians and the Chinese
soldiers are not quite as large and
strong as Indian soldiers on average
so and of course if the Chinese actually
succeed
in biting a piece of Indian Territory
I am sure this government will not take
that lying down and it could invite a
very massive and very heavy retaliation
maybe even non-conventional retaliation
and that is something the Chinese
simply don't want nobody wants to go
there
so I think they would be tempted to do
this but I don't think it makes any
sense for a sane rational Chinese leader
to indulge in a in a misadventure with
India
but India always has to keep this in
mind that the Chinese would want to do
to do this yeah so we have to be
eternally Vigilant semper vigilance like
they say in Latin and never ever
underestimate the enemy and never let
your guard down
um
right
where else are we and what else do we
have
harsh says did you watch Pony and selvan
the first the movies in the cholas yeah
the movie of the trollers yet how did
you like it I haven't watched it I've
been traveling the past week the next
week again I'm traveling a whole lot
so I don't know when I watch it I do
want to watch it I do want to watch it I
hear good things about it so I haven't
seen it but uh
I think when it comes to just five years
ago nobody knew about the cholas and I
think I was one of the first people to
start tweeting about the Chulas in
2016-2017 you know and now I'm so glad
that almost all Indians know about the
greatness of the Chola Empire the Chula
Dynasty and I hope the movie is good I
hope that it it portrays the history
accurately and I would certainly
like to see it whenever I get the
opportunity hopefully on the large
screen on the big screen not on a TV no
matter how big your TV is it's not it's
never the same as watching it in a
theater
so I certainly want to see it let me see
when I can get the opportunity and I
hope the movie doesn't go of the screens
soon because the next couple of weeks
I'm traveling a lot and I'm really busy
but yeah
I would like to see it for sure
um
rajat says PS1 is a great movie well I'm
so glad to hear that I'm so glad to hear
that I certainly look forward to
watching it
okay
an image says did Indian vessels and
satellites pound the Chinese spy vessel
that was docked at hammanthuta Port in
Sri Lanka eventually forcing it to
retreat and go back without it without
fulfilling its purpose
um
no as far as I know there was no
military action of any kind when we talk
about pounding something I'm I'm when
you say pound it it means kinetic action
which means you're pounding it with
missiles or artillery or shells or
whatever so yeah no such action was
taken that would obviously be military
action that would invite some kind of
retaliation from China
of
India China have an unstated agreement
of some kind that we don't take
we don't fire at each other right
even that galwan incident which happened
which was like brutal hand-to-hand
combat was uh in which maybe I don't
know how many Chinese died 70 80 100
Chinese died 20 Indians unfortunately
died at the hands of those barbarians so
that incident too was done without
firing a single shot it was
two groups of men fighting each other
with their bare hands and with clubs and
sticks and all that so India and China
have this unstated or or Unwritten
agreement that we will not fire at each
other so it doesn't make any sense for
India to I mean some people were saying
in the past that why in India quietly
sink that ship with are you people
kidding me those of you who say that uh
that's not how the world works you do
that you're gonna have retaliation then
that could escalate to any to it to any
extent
so India did not do any such thing
Indian vessels if you pound the Chinese
pie vessel it'd be destroyed right
if you pound it with missiles or with
the shells artillery whatever it is
that vessel will be destroyed then how
will it go back
and uh as far as I know we don't have
any satellites that are capable of
firing at Targets
on on the surface of the planet yeah
there are various concepts of satellite
based weapons you could place nukes on
satellites you could place missiles
possibly on satellites and you could
have kinetic weapons and satellites you
know non-explosive weapons uh the rods
from Gods from from God you know just
rods that travel at maybe around 50 20
30 kilometers per second even if it
travels at 10 kilometers per second or
even a kilometer per second just the
impact of a single Rod can destroy a
Target like take it out completely
so so various such Concepts do exist
they are certainly feasible the designs
I'm not sure if any country has
implemented that I'm sure many countries
have implemented various such uh
deployed certain such weapons but they
have never been revealed to the public
so I'm not sure if India is one of the
Nations that has satellized
satellite-based weapons but as far
as we know India has not taken any such
action against the Chinese
vessel Hearst says overwhelming it with
false signals to fill its data banks
so pounding in that manner we don't know
if we have done it we have not spoken
about it and the Chinese have also not
said anything about it so yeah this is
this is called electronic warfare
electronic countermeasures and all that
yeah
so that is something I'm sure India is
capable of doing if we have done it we
have not advertised it
a lot of warfare is based on Deception
all Warfare actually is based on
deception and when you score a victory
of any kind
oftentimes you don't want to advertise
it because that would lead to
uh public escalation
so even if India has done this India has
not advertised it so we don't know what
happened the the Chinese vessel
eventually did go away wherever it is
now so we don't know what steps were
taken by India I am sure certain steps
would have been taken but yeah we don't
know
all right
um
India when she crosses 10 trillion
dollars of GDP is it possible for her to
have visal States it's possible if India
so desires I'm sure India could do that
in the future it's certainly possible
Jaya Dixit says have you watched the
Kashmir files I regret to say I still
haven't watched it they never found the
time and perhaps it's a good thing I did
not watch it because I I hear it's a
very uh
it's a very brutal movie which depicts
what really happened but yeah it's it's
not pleasant to watch so I haven't
watched it
but I'm aware of what the story is about
yeah
um let us see some other questions uh
Hi5 repawn says can it speak about the
Richard structure in Mauritania and its
formation there are many Mysteries
surrounding it okay let's take a look at
the recharge structure in Mauritania so
where is Mauritania it is in Africa it's
in it's in Western Africa all right this
is the nation of Mauritania let's find
the reshat structure it is a
concentric series of things or whatever
let's see where is the recharge
structure I'm not sure if I can locate
it over here let's search for it
right and it's going to zoom in there
you go there we are
let's see what it looks like it's called
the eye of the Sahara
and they say this Atlantis here who who
decides this
I have no idea who decides this and I
don't know why why it says Atlantis and
if I hover my mouse over here I see John
Travolta from Pulp Fiction
what on Earth is that okay let's Zoom
further in
unfortunately I don't see much here
okay let's zoom out and see if we can
find something ah there you are there
you are so this is a weird structure
that looks like an impact crater but it
may most likely not be an impact Trader
and I'm not quite sure what the history
and the Mystery is about there is
something else similar to it over here
smaller thing yeah
so uh
I'm not sure how this was formed it is
most likely a naturally uh formed
structure I have obviously heard the
stories by various people claiming that
there are aliens here or maybe this is
Atlantis because if you read the story
of Atlantis by I don't know was it
plateau uh it said that Atlantis was was
constructed in a concentric Circle kind
of architectural thing and uh so this
does look like that but as far as I know
they have not found any evidence of
ancient human habitation over here
so yeah there are various theories and
stories about this some people claim
that this was constructed by an ancient
human civilization some people will
obviously claim that aliens are involved
um there was a guy I believe he came on
Joe Rogan's podcast and he spoke about
this I haven't seen it but I heard that
there was some discussion of this man of
this matter of the structure so yeah I'm
not quite sure how it was formed I've
never really investigated it it's an
interesting structure as you can see
it's uh it's very interesting the the
architecture right not the architecture
the the morphology of the structure most
likely it is a natural structure
but yeah interesting and I'm not sure
what kind of uh composition the rocks
have over here
uh the minerals the mineral composition
and all that so it's interesting it's
mysterious and I don't quite know about
it a lot about it
but yeah maybe I will investigate in the
future what it is all about
um all right um
okay
says where is the next episode of the
Indian interest are you planning to make
different types of content that you can
currently do in the near future uh thank
you sir uh yeah it's something that I
should indeed revive
I was doing this weekly geopolitics
podcast in which I was not taking
questions I was just talking about
things that I found that that were of
relevance for that week so yeah maybe I
will restart that because we are living
in very interesting times and a lot of
geopolitical action happening right now
so yeah I will certainly I do plan to
revive it and
hopefully in a week or two maybe maybe
in a couple of weeks one could have the
next episode of that yeah and other type
of content that I currently do
um I had
intended to make documentary style
videos but that obviously takes a lot of
time
so once I get a proper team in place to
do all the
all the non-creative work of the editing
and all that then I would certainly want
to do much more and expand into other
kinds of content like documentary style
videos maybe in-person podcasts all that
let's see how it goes I would certainly
like to do much more of that yes
all right uh let us see
what else do we have
um
Rahul says your Vlogs
um maybe maybe Vlogs too perhaps you
know the Vlogs are interesting
Vlogs are typically interesting when
you're traveling and you're experiencing
different things and those experiences
those interactions that's what makes
blog Vlogs interesting one of the most
famous vloggers of all time is the
American guy Casey neistat his Vlogs
were so interesting because each block
had a certain story
uh it had a three-act structure and
there were multiple characters multiple
locations a lot of traveling and all
that so that's what makes Vlogs
interesting compelling that's what Hooks
the audience if it's just me sitting
here and talking about various things
then it's it's not very much different
from what I'm already doing
so uh if I do travel and you know what
it's not easy to make blogs especially
if you are the only person filming you
got to hold a camera in front of you and
while traveling it's it's really it's
really difficult to do that so maybe I
will do vlogs in the future possibly if
I can figure out a way of doing it
sustainably possibly perhaps that's not
what the channel is obviously focused on
but yeah I have a vlog Channel which uh
I have a vlog Channel which I have not
updated for updated for many months uh
the only Vlogs I've done on the channel
are my documentation or me documenting
my water fasts
so yeah I I have this I once in a while
I do a water fast which is a very
dangerous thing to do but I do that so
that's typically what I document in
those Vlogs not more than that maybe
something else I'll do in the future
let's see
um
uh right let's see what else other
questions
um
one spot says according to you which
leader has been by far the best for
India except sriishi neruji
uh okay look uh
um
so
there have been multiple leaders as we
know uh we have the great magnificent
three deruji who obviously
I mean
he's the greatest of all time no no no
question about it so if we put Mr nehru
Jason because he's too great for anybody
else then we had uh Mr shastri Mr Lal
bahadur shastri then we had Mrs Gandhi
who was in power for a long time then
you had a
then you heard Mr Desai Mr Muradi Desai
who was in power for a brief period of
time
when we had Mr Rajiv Gandhi then we had
two or three very short tenured Prime
Ministers Mr HD devagoda Mr uh gujral
and Mr shekhar
then we had Mr vajpayee then we had the
another magnificent person the great Mr
the great doctor Manmohan Singh we had
obviously Mr Bibi nurse him at all
and after Mr manmohon Singh it is it has
been Mr Modi so we have had all these
various people I think one of the most
consequential Prime Ministers was Mrs
Gandhi
she uh
shaped India's
well the way India progressed to a great
extent
she uh did bifurcate Pakistan she it was
under her tenure as prime minister that
Bangladesh was liberated from Pakistan
which is a great thing uh and various
other things as well
certain problematic things also happened
during her as history tells us
and yeah so we've had
a variety of prime ministers
was one of the uh people who most most
observers neglect
he did uh he lasted history lasted five
years he's the one who opened up India's
economy we were forced to do that
because the Indian economy was almost
bankrupt India had almost gone bankrupt
India's foreign exchange reserves were
enough for two or three days only so
India because of mismanagement by by
previous uh Prime Ministers and regimes
had been become almost completely
bankrupt so India was forced to open up
its economy
on the terms of the West and that's
where things start going bad for India
infiltration by Western
uh
actors and all that but overall business
was I think a good prime minister so I'm
not sure who has been the best thus far
I will not talk about the present prime
minister and I will not talk about this
nehru apart from the others they all had
certain strengths they all had certain
weaknesses they all did something good I
I suppose all of them most of them would
have done something good for the nation
some did more good than the others some
did more bad than the others so uh
so yeah it's I think it's up to you all
to decide who you think was good for
India or the best for for India uh
obviously Mr nehru Nobody can come
anywhere close to him he was that
magnificent and it is too early for us
to say anything about Mr Modi uh once
somebody's once a certain prime minister
senior is over we can look back uh and
and uh examine with the benefit of
hindsight how the tenure has been so
while somebody is serving it is from I I
feel that it is best not to pass any
Judgment at that time right but I think
Mr Modi is doing a brilliant job yeah
all right oh
the man himself is here obviously it's
no I don't blame you sir Mr nehru you
are the most magnificent of them all
right let us see what other questions we
have
um
uh Hindu share Putin says will Africa
ever be free from foreign occupation and
neocolonization uh Africa has
a tragic history the past four three
four hundred five hundred years
tragic history the Europeans have
destroyed Africa entirely
entirely
today they pretend like they are they're
out of Africa they're not they're still
actively destroying Africa various
European nations I will not take names
because some of them are on our side for
some in some in some ways so let's not
go there but yeah
I would like to see Africa free from
colonization Africa's culture has been
destroyed Africa's indigenous religions
have been wiped out Africa had its own
system various African kingdoms and
regions had their own systems of
Governors they had their own beautiful
culture everything has been destroyed
completely
the people of Africa have been reduced
to
to destitution
there have been strict stripped of all
dignity
that's what poverty does to people you
may be the most advanced culture in the
world the most advanced civilization in
the world but if you become destitute if
you are in poverty you are stripped of
your dignity that's what happens so
that's what the Europeans have done to
Africa over and obviously there's been
horrific genocides in Africa so and
today you have new colonization from
various European actors and even
while the Chinese yeah the Chinese are
are up to their old games in Africa the
debt trap diplomacy and and various
Western Nations prop up various African
dictators you know who's the favorite
dictator of the West it's the person
who's ruling Rwanda right now Rwanda is
a nation in Africa there was a
there was a terrible genocide that
happened in Rwanda
about 20 or so years before today uh
let's put the map on
and the civil war in Rwanda the genocide
that happened there the Hutu versus
Tutsi issue it was all
uh
instigated by the Catholic Church
right this small nation here so for the
past 20 or so years the Rwanda has had a
person who has ruled the nation but one
the president let me Google that
okay Paul kagame
there's a person called Paul kagame who
is the president so-called president of
urwanda let's put this gentleman on the
screen so he has been the president of
Rwanda since 2000. now if whenever an
African president or leader lasts that
long it is only because that person
isn't the good good books of the West
and we speak when we speak about the
West we know who we're speaking about
so this person is providing various
services to the West in exchange for
which that person is allowed to stay in
power so this gentleman Mr Paul kagame
he is called uh the West's favorite
dictator he has been in power for
for 22 years can you believe it 22 years
so that's what the vest does in Africa
they
they put puppets in power
people who are essentially dictators
nothing has nothing nothing but
dictators and they're allowed to stay in
power as long as they allow the West to
plunder and pillage and pilfer the
country for resources and extract
everything of value out of there so
there are various African nations that
are extremely rich in Mineral wealth in
gold and yet the people are incredibly
poor these nations have no gold reserves
but the gold goes somewhere so that's
what's being been done being done even
today to Africa
so will Africa ever be free from foreign
occupation and neocolonization I hope so
I hope so this will happen when there is
a new uh
New Way New World Order which is not
um ruled by the West
yeah for that India will have to rise
it's it's still a long way away and
that's what the West doesn't want to
happen they don't want India to rise
they want to keep on plundering and
and uh doing that blundering the world
and exploiting the poor people of the
world and the poor nations of the world
which they have impoverished
so that's how it is you know and the
world is not as nice a place as we think
it is
um
India was the sixth largest economy in
1947 now fifth really
as far as I know India's GDP India's
share of the world's GDP had dropped to
below two percent in 1947.
was it the sixth largest economy in 1947
I don't think so
all right what else
Shaheen says do you agree that the
chanake Niti shastra should be taught in
our schools
um when it comes to schools I think the
chanaky Niti and the Chana can uh
philosophy
uh is a little Advanced for that you
know for the school level it's something
that should be taught in in maybe in
political science
uh maybe at the college and university
level not in the school and high school
level but yes if some students are
interested they can certainly acquire
the books for themselves I have the
shastra somewhere here
I believe this is the one if I'm not
mistaken so I have the Arthur shastra if
you're interested you can study it on
your own but I think that for most
students uh studying it at the school
level would be uh would be too too much
to ask for it would be good ones it's
certainly something you could study at
the college level and certainly at the
University level I think all diplomats
should be uh
required to study this
and uh
yeah it's something that's certainly
very useful in diplomacy in geopolitics
yeah
uh yeah so it's something that you can
study at an advanced level not at the
school level but it's certainly
something that we should include in our
curriculum at the appropriate level
all right
all right let's see um
how is it that the U.S has so many Nobel
Peace prizes isn't it ironic isn't it
ironic that's a song by Alanis
Morissette ironic yes it is ironic the
the U.S has so many Nobel Peace prizes
these Nobel prices are are these are
shops that are given to those who who
serve the West
so that's how it goes and yeah I mean
imagine giving the Nobel Peace Prize to
Barack Obama before he did anything at
all as U.S president
and he eventually ended up dropping more
bombs on innocent people than his
predecessor George W bush so yeah and
and one of the lower Nobel Peace prizes
went to Henry Kissinger who was anything
but peaceful yeah so that's how it is
you know so it's ironic it's it's
hypocrisy
it tells you that we should not take
these prizes so seriously
okay Sai Suman says please start
channels in Telugu and other languages
too for reaching a wider audience so I I
regret that I don't speak Telugu but
yeah in the future if I would if I could
collaborate from people whose mother
tongue is Telugu then I could certainly
uh one could explore such things in the
future I personally unfortunately do not
speak Telugu so as of now it's it's not
possible but it's certainly something I
will keep in mind maybe in the future I
may have the opportunity to explore
something like this for sure
all right uh lots and lots of questions
are coming in we are reaching the end of
today's session but let's see some more
um
uncovered says can India break free from
anti-india forces within India
India can break free of all its issues
internal as well as is external
in due time
in due time right now India is still not
at the stage where it can
uh
it can see right now what's happening is
that yes you're right there are
anti-india forces within India it's what
the late General bipin Singh rawats
referred to as the 2.5 front War which
means that one front is China One front
is Pakistan and there is half a friend
from within India itself you know
and these uh
various anti-india forces that exist
within India are all funded and financed
from outside of India that's how it
happens the moment the funding is
slipped away once the money stops
flowing all these things will end
now why isn't the government doing it
because the money the reason why the
government is currently not cracking
down all on all of them is because the
money the financing is coming up coming
into India from
forces that are way too powerful for
India right now they're coming from
superpowers
yeah
so uh now is not the time but eventually
India will
uh it's not about cracking down on
people and doing any such thing you know
it's just about cutting cutting away
cutting off the sources of funding the
moment the money stops flowing these
people will stop their activities
they're doing it for money these people
are mercenaries they are for hire
you pay them more money they will do
whatever you want them to do it that's
how it goes some in any society you have
some people who are like this yeah so
when the time is right it will be done
and India will indeed be free from
anti-india forces from within
all right all right
um
uh what happened to Muhammad bin Salman
what is the recent controversy or
incident of Muhammad bin Salman Prince
of Saudi Arabia I'm not aware of it
um controversy incident I haven't heard
of anything if something happened in the
past two series I may not have heard of
it I was busy traveling but uh
let's see if something comes to my
notice I will speak about this
ah yeah this is a good question how many
countries with independent foreign
policies still exist today India to a
large extent has an independent foreign
policy China has an independent foreign
policy it is not dictated by other
external forces so you have China you
have India you have Russia we all
operate within the constraints that we
for with that that exist in the
International System so India is there
China is there Russia is there the us
obviously has its independent foreign
policy and it forces other nations to to
fall in line with that policy within
Europe I think France to some extent has
a quasi or semi-independent foreign
policy to some extent uh but on on a lot
of issues they are forced to
to accede to U.S demand so for instance
France supports Ukraine in its uh in the
Ukraine conflict right against Russia so
in that case you see that France has the
same policy as the U.S
and so on so forth so uh France has a
semi-independent foreign policy Israel
has a semi-independent foreign policy in
Israel to a large extent depends on the
support in the in Alliance from the U.S
so Israel's foreign policy also to some
extent or to a large extent or to a
medium extent moderate extent would be
dictated by by the United States
and what else can I think of which Other
Nation the UK is a non-entity
in in Europe it's only France that has a
somewhat independent foreign policy so I
would say among the major nations in the
world Iran has a reasonably independent
foreign policy they are constrained by
their dependence on on China to a some
extent and to some extent on Russia as
well yeah
so India China Russia
and the US these nations have reasonably
USS completely independent China is
largely Independent India is largely
independent and Russia is largely
independent so these are the four major
Nations that have independent foreign
policies the other nations are all in
some way or the other
uh bending to the will of a larger
nation and most of it is is done at the
behalf of the US
who would win a war between chandragupta
maurya and chingis Khan
first of all
would not fight they would have no
reason to fight each other
right so Chandra Gupta maurya had a
simple objective to unify the Indian
subcontinent politically that's what he
wanted to do he was not an expansionist
in the sense of wanting to expand and
Conquer into other territories that were
not Indian historically right
um so chandrakupta was not an
expansionist and
he uh so and and Genghis Khan always
fought Wars in retaliation
he didn't start start any of the wars he
fought but he did respond and he
destroyed whatever enemies his people
had so uh
so I don't see any reason for the two to
actually want to fight each other at all
now if a war actually happened who would
win we're not quite sure uh if you look
at history I mean if you look at overall
how things went uh one would have to
kind of favor changes Khan because he
never lost any any military campaign
that he ever fought after he became the
emperor of the Mongols as when he was
rising to power the internal power
struggle in Mongolia he had numerous
setback setbacks
but he always emerged stronger from that
and after he became the great Khan of
the Mongols he did not lose a single
military campaign he would have lost a
few battles here and there but a
military campaign is an extended uh
campaign with multiple battles it has a
political objective and a military
objective he did not lose a single
military campaign ever he overwhelmed
and routed all his opponents no matter
how big how great how strong how
powerful they were
so considering that track record that he
had he owned essentially at one point in
time nearly half the world in half the
known world if you consider that that
track record in mind it would one would
have to
one would have to uh bet in favor of
Genghis Khan yeah
but there is no real reason they would
have ever fought each other because
there was no need for them to fight each
other and we know that they existed at
very different points in time
all right all right let's take one more
question shall we or are we done
so let's take one more interesting
question
Mr Giga chat of India will Elise lose
power in the UK earlier than Boris
Johnson as she has been unable unable to
save the economy of the UK please
understand this my dear friends the UK
is a vasal state of the U.S if you look
at the history of the past two decades
in the UK It's A procession of
insignificant prime minister who come
and go who come and go some last for a
while some last for a very short period
of time uh there was this guy called
Gordon Brown who was there for a few
years and then there was
what's the other guy's name
um the one who succeeded him who was
before him I don't even remember the
names that's how insignificant these
peoples are these people are these Prime
Ministers are all non-entities they
don't do anything they don't they don't
achieve much it's just like what the
Americans have done to Japan apart from
shinzhou no other Japanese prime
minister was allowed to continue or was
able to continue for more than a couple
of years to three years here and there
uh David Cameron there is a May yeah
yeah Landmark says David Cameron and sir
and Rahul says tourism thank you thank
you for reminding me
yeah so uh the question was about Liz
truss she's another non-entity and some
people get upset when I say that well
deal with it she is a non-entity and I
don't see her ever being able to make
any significant uh impact on the UK
until says I think chingis Khan invaded
Japan correct me if I wrong if I'm wrong
it wasn't chingis Khan who invaded Japan
it was his grandson Kublai Khan who
attempted to invade Japan and it did not
go well because of divine intervention
the divine wind Kabhi khaze Kami means
god or or deity in Japan so so uh uh
Kublai Khan attempted invading Japan and
it is the Divine typhoons the divine
wind that destroyed the in the The
Invasion Fleet of the Mongol Empire
which was then ruled from Beijing
because because of History what happened
in history so Chinese Khan did not ever
try invading Japan the Mongol Empire did
under his grandson Kublai Khan all right
my dear friends thank you very much for
a wonderful session wonderful questions
all over again and let's do this again
tomorrow tomorrow will be more focused
questions tomorrow I will take questions
from your comments and we will deal more
with geopolitics and history so thank
you very much once again for all the
questions always great fun taking the
questions from the live chat
and I will see you very soon I will see
you tomorrow until then take care
thank you bye